Dan Amrhein

NSF Postdoctoral Fellow University of Washington amrhein.github.io amrhein@uw.edu

My research combines numerical models and observations of the natural world to learn about the dynamics of Earth's oceans and climate in the present, future, and geologic past.

INTERESTS: CLIMATE DYNAMICS, PHYSICAL OCEANOGRAPHY, INVERSE MODELING, DATA ASSIMILATION, NUMERICAL MODELING, PALEOCLIMATOLOGY

Education

2016 MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY

WOODS HOLE OCEANOGRAPHIC INSTITUTION

Ph.D. in Physical Oceanography: Inferring Ocean Circulation during the Last Glacial Max-

imum and Last Deglaciation Using Data and Models

Adviser: Carl Wunsch

2014 MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY

WOODS HOLE OCEANOGRAPHIC INSTITUTION

M.S. in Physical Oceanography: An inverse approach to understanding benthic oxygen

isotope records from the last deglaciation

Adviser: Carl Wunsch

2009 COLUMBIA COLLEGE, COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY

Bachelor of Arts in Physics with a Concentration in Mathematics, May 2009

Employment

2017– NSF Postdoctoral Fellow, University of Washington

Dept. of Atmospheric Sciences and School of Oceanography

Mentors: Greg Hakim and LuAnne Thompson

2016–17 Postdoctoral Research Associate, University of Washington

Dept. of Atmospheric Sciences and School of Oceanography

Mentors: Greg Hakim and LuAnne Thompson

2009-10 Research Assistant, Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory, Columbia University

Supervisors: Jason Smerdon and Alexey Kaplan

Grants and Awards

pending

NSF Paleoclimate Perspectives on Climate Change. *Quantifying spatial footprints of planktic foraminifera in marine sediments and exploring implications for past ocean variability and model-data synthesis.* Could not be Co-PI because of departmental policy, but contributed to ideas and writing.

pending NASA ROSES Physical Oceanography. Beyond budgets: Inferring sensitivities of North Atlantic heat and salt contents to atmospheric variability using ECCO and its adjoint. Co-I. 2017-19 NSF Atmospheric and Geospace Sciences Postdoctoral Fellowship: Inferring Predictability and Dynamics of Atlantic Multidecadal Climate Variability from Marine and Terrestrial Paleoclimate Records. \$172,000 2017 Ocean Outlook Fellow at the University of Bergen 2012-15 NSF Graduate Research Fellow MIT Presidential Fellow 2010-11 2007 AGU travel grant, IUGG meeting, Perugia, Italy. 2006 George William Curtis Prize in Oration at Columbia College

Teaching Experience

2018	Guest lecturer on adjoint modeling, Ensemble Prediction Systems, ATM S 544
2014-16	Developed and taught MIT 12.091 MATLAB Bootcamp
2014-16	Organized a department graduate mentorship program at MIT
2015	Taught classes in Statistics, Linear Algebra, and MATLAB as a WHOI summer instructor
2014	Completed the MIT Teaching Certification Program
2013-14	Mentored a junior graduate student through MIT departmental program
2009	Teaching Assistant for Earth and Environmental Sciences W2330, <i>Science for Sustainable Development</i> , Columbia University

Peer-Reviewed Research Publications

subm. **Amrhein, D. E.** How large are temporal representativeness errors in paleoclimatology? Submitted to *Climate of the Past*.

subm. P. Moffa-Sánchez, E. Moreno-Chamarro, D. J. Reynolds, P. Ortega, L. Cunningham, D. Swingedouw, **D. E. Amrhein**, J. Halfar, L. Jonkers, J. H. Jungclaus, K. Perner, A. Wanamaker and S. Yeager. Variability in the northern North Atlantic and Arctic oceans across the last two millennia: A review. Subm. to *Paleoceanography and Paleoclimatology*.

subm. Zhang, R., R. Sutton, G. Danabasoglu, Y.-O. Kwon, R. Marsh, S. Yeager, **D. E. Amrhein**, and C. Little. A Review of the Role of AMOC Variability in Atlantic Multidecadal Variability and Associated Climate Impacts. Submitted to *Rev. Geophysics*.

- Amrhein, D. E., C. Wunsch, O. Marchal, and G. Forget. A global glacial state estimate constrained by upper-ocean temperature proxies. *Journal of Climate*, https://doi.org/10.1175/JCLI-D-17-0769.1.
- Zhao, Ning, O. Marchal, L. Keigwin, **D. E. Amrhein**, and G. Gebbie. A synthesis of deglacial deep-sea radiocarbon records and a test of their (in)consistency with modern ocean circulation. *Paleoceanography and Paleoclimatology*, onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/2017PA003174.
- Amrhein, D. E., G. Gebbie, O. Marchal, and C. Wunsch. Inferring surface water equilibrium calcite δ^{18} O during the last deglacial period from benthic foraminiferal δ^{18} O records: Implications for ocean circulation. *Paleoceanography*, onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/2014PA002743.
- Smerdon, J.E., A. Kaplan, and **D. E. Amrhein**. Reply to Comment on "Erroneous Model Field Representations in Multiple Pseudoproxy Studies: Corrections and Implications," *Journal of Climate.*, https://doi.org/10.1175/JCLI-D-12-00165.1.
- Bower, A.S., R. M. Hendry, **D. E. Amrhein**, and J. M. Lilly. Direct Observations of Formation and Propagation of Subpolar Eddies into the Subtropical North Atlantic, *Deep Sea Research Part II: Topical Studies in Oceanography*, http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.dsr2.2012.07.029.
- 2010 Smerdon, J.E., A. Kaplan, and **D.E. Amrhein**. Erroneous Model Field Representations in Multiple Pseudoproxy Studies: Corrections and Implications, *Journal of Climate*, https://doi.org/10.1175/2010JCLI3742.1.

Publications in preparation

- in prep. **Amrhein, D.E.** and G. Hakim. Quantifying knowability in paleoclimate data assimilation. In prep. for *Climate of the Past*.
- in prep. **Amrhein, D.E.**, C. Wunsch, and L. Thompson. Dynamical controls on the depth of the boundary between bottom and deep waters in the Last Glacial Maximum Atlantic. In prep. for *J. of Geophysical Research: Oceans*.
- in prep. **Amrhein, D.E.** and L. Thompson. Methods for accelerating and extrapolating tracer equilibration in numerical ocean models. In prep. for *Ocean Modeling*.
- in prep. Hakim, G., **D. E. Amrhein**, C. Snyder, D. N. Anderson, J. Emile-Geay, D. Noone, and R. Tardif. Quantifying Proxy Influence in the Last Millennium Reanalysis. In prep. for *Climate of the Past*.

Invited talks and seminars

Quantifying uncertainty in data and models towards reconstructing past AMOC variability. AMOC Paleo Task Team webinar.

2018 Estimating the abyssal ocean state at the Last Glacial Maximum by assimilating ocean tracer measurements into numerical models. Oregon State University Quaternary Science Tea, Corvallis, OR. 2017 How large are aliasing errors due to sampling paleoclimate records discontinuously? Climate and Paleoclimate Seminar, Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, Woods Hole, MA. 2017 A glacial ocean state estimate constrained by upper ocean temperature proxies. Physical Oceanography Department Seminar, University of Washington, Seattle, WA. 2017 Connecting the future to the past using ocean models. Ocean Outlook Meeting, Bergen, Norway. 2016 Inferring Circulation During the Last Glacial Maximum and Last Deglaciation using

Conference Presentations

Quantifying errors in paleoclimate reconstructions arising from assumed spatial covariances. D. E. Amrhein and G. Hakim. Climate Variability Across Scales (CVAS) meeting, Seattle, WA.

Data and Models. Physical Oceanography Dissertation Symposium, Honolulu, HI.

- Dynamical controls on the depth of the boundary between bottom and deep waters in the Last Glacial Maximum Atlantic. D. E. Amrhein and L. Thompson. AMOC Science Team meeting, Miami, FL.
- Probing the limits of knowability in paleoclimate reconstructions of the last millennium. (Oral presentation) D. E. Amrhein and G. Hakim. University of Washington Program on Climate Change Spring Symposium, Seattle, WA.
- 2018 Reconstruction of last-millennium atmosphere and ocean quantities and quantification of spatiotemporal uncertainty. (Oral presentation) D. E. Amrhein, G. Hakim, and L. Thompson. European Geophysical Union meeting, Vienna, Austria.
- Dynamical controls on the depth of the boundary between bottom and deep waters in the Last Glacial Maximum Atlantic. D. E. Amrhein, L. Thompson, and C. Wunsch. PALMOD International Open Science Conference, Vienna, Austria.
- Dynamical controls on the depth of the boundary between bottom and deep waters in the Last Glacial Maximum Atlantic. (Oral presentation) D. E. Amrhein, L. Thompson, and C. Wunsch. Ocean Sciences meeting, Portland, OR.
- 2018 Connecting deep ocean tracer observations to surface temperature, precipitation, and wind stress. (Oral presentation). D. E. Amrhein, L. Thompson, and C. Wunsch. Workshop on Using Past Observations to Constrain Future Climate Variability, Seattle, WA.
- Discontinuous sampling aliases paleoclimate records. D. E. Amrhein. PAGES Workshop on Data Assimilation and Proxy System Modeling, Louvain-la-Neuve, Belgium.

2017 Annual to multidecadal coherence of Atlantic meridional heat transport in last-millennium CMIP5 simulations and the Last Millennium Reanalysis. D. E. Amrhein, G. Hakim, L. Thompson, and K. Armour. CLIVAR AMOC Science Team Meeting, Santa Fe, NM. 2016 Estimating past ocean states using data and models. (Oral Presentation). D. E. Amrhein. Physical Oceanography Department Seminar, Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, Woods Hole, MA 2016 Constructing simple predictive models from paleoclimate records. D. E. Amrhein, G. Hakim, and L. Thompson. AGU Fall Meeting, San Francisco, CA. 2016 Towards an LGM state estimate. (Oral Presentation). D. E. Amrhein. ECCO Joint Project Meeting, Cambridge, MA. 2015 GOSE: A Glacial Ocean State Estimate. (Oral Presentation). D. E. Amrhein and C. Wusnch. AGU Fall Meeting, San Francisco, CA. 2015 GOSE: A Glacial Ocean State Estimate. (Oral Presentation). D. E. Amrhein and C. Wusnch. Graduate Climate Conference, Woods Hole, MA. Inferring surface water equilibrium calcite δ^{18} O during the last deglacial period from 2014 benthic foraminiferal δ^{18} O records: Implications for ocean circulation. D. E. Amrhein, G. Gebbie, O. Marchal, and C. Wunsch. AGU Fall Meeting, San Francisco, CA. Inferring surface water equilibrium calcite δ^{18} O during the last deglacial period from 2014 benthic foraminiferal δ^{18} O records: Implications for ocean circulation. (Oral presentation) D. E. Amrhein, G. Gebbie, O. Marchal, and C. Wunsch. iPODS-OC3 meeting, Bern, Switzerland. Constraining Deglacial Climate Using Sediment Core Records of δ^{18} O: An Inverse 2013 Methods Approach. (Oral Presentation) D. E. Amrhein and C. Wunsch. Advanced Climate Dynamics Course Summer School, Nyksund, Norway. 2009 A Pseudoproxy-Ensemble Study of Late-Holocene Climate Field Reconstructions Using CCA. D. E. Amrhein, J. Smerdon, and A. Kaplan. AGU Fall Meeting, San Francisco, CA. 2008 How do distinct physical phenomena and processes affect spectral slopes of climate variables? D. E. Amrhein and A. Kaplan. Ocean Sciences Meeting, Orlando, FL. 2007 How do weather, insolation, and interannual phenomena affect spectral slopes of climate variables? D. E. Amrhein and A. Kaplan. IUGG General Assembly Meeting, Perugia, Italy. 2006 Characterization of climatological power laws via ratios of interannual to subannual variance. D. E. Amrhein and A. Kaplan. AGU Fall Meeting, San Francisco, CA.

Professional Training

2017 GeoHackWeek participant: one-week course on Python and data science, Seattle, WA

2013 Advanced Climate Dynamics Course, Nyksund, Versterålen, Norway

2008	Summer Student Fellow, Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution Supervisor: Amy Bower (Physical Oceanography)
2007	Summer School in the Physics of the Climate System, Utrecht University, Utrecht, Netherlands
2006–09	Undergraduate Research Assistant, LDEO, Columbia University Supervisor: Alexey Kaplan (Ocean and Climate Physics)

Field Experience

2017	Cruise from Woods Hole, MA to Azores, Portugal. Piston, gravity, and multicore sediment sampling to study glacial carbon isotopes
2015	Field course on the US East Coast. Coastal geomorphology and anthropogenic changes
2014	Field course in Massif Central, France and Iceland. Volcanism and mid-ocean ridges
2013	Field course in Kona, HI. Earth's gravitational field
2010	Cruise from Bermuda to Woods Hole. Physical and biological oceanographic sampling

Professional Service

- 2018 Co-organizer, AGU Session PP41F. New Perspectives on Past Climates: Progress in Proxy System Modeling, Reconstruction Algorithms, and Uncertainty Quantification.
- 2018 Past Global Changes (PAGES) early career liaison
- 2017 Participant, AMOC Science Team
- 2017 Participant, Data Assimilation and Proxy System Modeling working group, PAGES
- 2012-14 Organizing Committee, Annual retreat for the MIT Program on Atmospheres, Oceans, and Climate

Reviewer for Journal of Climate and Climate Dynamics

Recent Outreach Activities

STEM Ambassador, Edmonds School District's 6th Annual STEM Expo
 Lecture on climate change and ocean acidification, Shoreline Community College, Shoreline, WA
 Demonstration volunteer, Shoreline STEMfest, Shoreline, WA
 Script writer for UW Atmospheric Sciences Video Outreach

Professional Skills

Highly proficient with the MITgcm, MATLAB, Python, Linux/Unix, \LaTeX SCUBA open water certified